你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎收看另一个PWN大学视频
welcome to another pwn college video
今天我们将讨论ASLR
today we'll be talking about ASLR
这是对内存错误的保护措施
it's a mitigation for memory errors
特别是控制流劫持攻击
specifically control flow hijack attacks
它代表地址空间布局随机化
and it stands for adderss space layout randomization
好吧
all right
地址空间布局随机化背后的思想是什么
what is the idea behind address space layout randomization
当然，其思想是随机化地址空间的布局
of course the idea is to randomize the layout of the address space
很多时候
the intuition here is that oftentimes
当利用内存错误时
when exploiting a memory error
你破坏了指针
you corrupt a pointer
攻击者破坏指针
the attacker corrupts a pointer
让它指向别的地方
to make it point somewhere else
这个指针可能是一个代码指针
that pointer might be a code pointer
攻击者想要劫持控制代码执行流
and the attacker wants to hijack control flow
指针可以是数据指针
the pointer might be a data pointer
攻击者想要控制数据权限
and the attacker wants to perform controlled data right
但是每当攻击者重写指针时
but whenever the attacker overwrites a pointer
他们必须要知道指向哪里
they have to have an idea of where to point it to
他们能做到
and they can do that
因为例如，如果你编译时不开启位置无关
because for example if you compile a program as not position independent
攻击者能查看二进制文件，找到程序驻留在内存中的位置
the attacker can look at the binary and see where in a memory that program will reside
但是如果你打开地址空间布局随机化
but if you turn on address space layout randomization
随机化栈和堆的位置
and you randomize where the stack is where the heap is
main函数的位置
and where the main program is
库的位置
where all the libraries are
攻击者就没有这些信息了
suddenly the attacker doesn't have that information and
控制流劫持和任意覆盖攻击要困难得多
has a much harder time executing these control flow hijack and controlled overwrite attacks
看一下示例
let's take a look at what I mean by this
在之前的视频中，我们有一个缓冲区溢出的简单例子
we have our buffer overflow very simple example from a prior video
编译一下
let's compile it
我这次还要关闭栈保护
I'm going to turn off stack protections again
嗯
um
啊，打错了
ah there's no stack protector
好吧
alright
如果你还记得
and if you recall
第一次用它演示缓冲区溢出时，我禁用了位置无关代码
the 1st time this came out I disabled position independent code
如果我 objectdump 这个 bufferoverflow
so here if I do an object dump on this buffer overflow
它总是会映射到这些位置，对吧
it is always going to be mapped at these locations right
所以预测很简单
so it's simple to predict
在之前的视频中我利用这个时
in the previous video where I exploited this
我只是使用这个确切的地址来覆盖返回地址
I simply used that exact address to overwrite the return address with
所以很简单
so it was very simple
但如果你没有关闭这个时
but what if you don't have this
现在是什么样子
what does it look like now
现在看起来不一样了
now it looks different right
这些是程序加载时在内存中的偏移量
these are offsets in memory where this program will be loaded and
如果我们运行这个bufferoverflow
if we just run this bufferoverflow and we
在另一个窗口（执行bufferoverflow）
in a different window
读出内存映射
read out the memory mapping
我们看到它被随机映射到某个地方
we see it got mapped somewhere random
它的库被随机映射到某个地方
its libraries got mapped somewhere random
加载器，也是它的库，随机映射到某个地方
the loader another one of its libraries got maps somewhere random
栈被随机映射到某个地方
the stack got maps somewhere random
如果我们再运行一次
and if we rerun this again
所有这些都是不同的
all of these are different
原来是55f6
so it used to be 5 5 F6
现在是5619等等
now it's 5 6 1 9 and so on
一直到这个数字都有较大的随机性
high amount of randomness right down to this number
这个第四个最低有效的半个字节
this very the 4th least significant half byte
顺便说一下，半个字节叫做半字节
1/2 a byte by the way is called the nibble
所以一直到第4个最低有效的半字节会被随机化
so right down to the 4th least significant nibble things are randomized
这对攻击者来说是个坏消息
this is bad news for an attacker
好了，让我们回到幻灯片
alright so let's roll back to the slides
先研究这是怎么出现的
and dive into 1st how this came about
然后看看我们能做些什么
and then what we can do about it so
ASLR首次出现于2001年
ASLR 1st appeared in 2001
作为Linux安全补丁集PaX的一部分
as part of a Linux security patch set called PaX
这个补丁集放在今天也是很重要的
it packs as a patch set that is still relevant today
在Linux内核中实现了大量的安全概念缓保护机制
man has implements that a whole lot of security concepts mitigations in the linux kernel
他们也为下一个内核版本提供了数据执行保护（DEP）
these are also the people that brought data execution Protection to the the next kernel
这是一个
it's a
这也是防御工具箱中非常有效的工具
which is a very also a very effective tool in the defense toolbox and
我在shellcode模块中讲过
that I talked about in the shell code module
有趣的是，PaX是由一个匿名的程序员领导的
interestingly the PaX is led by an anonymous coder
这是一件有趣的事情
so that's an interesting thing
这是他们的吉祥物
this is their mascot
它是经过苦战版的Linux吉祥物
it's a battle hardened version of the Linux mascot
这是他们向世界展示自己的方式
and that is how they present themselves to the world
但在2001年，他们创建了ASLR
but in 2001 they created ASLR
提交到Linux
added to submitted to Linux
2005年，Linux终于在内核主线中发布了ASLR
2005 is when Linux finally shipped ASLR in the main line of kernel
openBSD在默认配置下启用所有ASLR，比Linux快了两年
open BSD beat Linux by two years in enabling all ASLR on a default configuration
但在
but around
2001到2005年，地址空间随机布局开始兴起
between 2001 and 2005 is this rise of address space layout randomization
现在所有东西都是随机化的
all right so now everything is randomized
栈在一个随机的位置
the stacks at a random location
即使在该程序中没有使用堆，它也位于随机位置
the heap even though it wasn't used in that program is at a random location
我们还可以做什么
what do we do
我们还可以做一些事情
there's still a couple of things that we could do
一这些地址还是在内存的某个地方
one is those addresses are in memory somewhere
如果你还有漏洞，我们就可以泄露出来
so we could leak them out if you had another vulnrability
听起来像是金丝雀一样，不是吗
sounds like the canary case doesn't it
我们现在必须有一个新的漏洞来泄漏内存中的位置
we have to have now a new vulnrability to leak out the location in memory
抱歉
sorry
我们需要第二个弱点
we need to have a 2nd vulnrability
泄漏内存中各种库、二进制文件、堆栈等的基址
to leak out the base addresses of various libraries binaries the stack etc in memory
这
this
这表明ASLR是一种非常有效的缓解措施
this shows that ASLR is a very effective mitigation
和栈金丝雀一样
like stack canary
我们很难忽略ASLR
it is very hard to simply ignore ASLR
而ASLR确实大大提高了攻击者利用软件的门槛
and ASLR really raised the bar significantly for attackers to be able to exploit software
另一种方法
another method
我们会更深入一点
that we'll go in in depth a little bit
基本上是YOLO它
is basically to YOLO it
要意识到程序资产是对齐的
to realize that the program assets are aligned
页面映射的地址是对齐的
pages are mapped at aligned locations
你看，最后三个半字节都是零
you see all these last three nibbles are all zeros
为了更好地解释这个问题，我们将在第二部分中深入讲解
and to leverage that for explication we'll cover that in a 2nd in depth
第三种方法适用于使用fork的服务
and a 3rd method for forking services
和我们对栈金丝雀做的一样
is to do the exact same thing we did for stack canary
用暴力破解的方法
to brute force them
如果你有使用fork的服务
again if you have a forking service
只是在一开始
things are only really randomized at the beginning
当父进程启动时，是随机的
of the when the original process the parent process launches up
父进程fork出的每个子进程
every childhood the parent process forks off
都是父进程的副本
will be a copy of the parent process
包括栈金丝雀，包括ASLR后的库偏移量
including the stack canary and including the ASLR library offsets
这和我们在栈金丝雀案例中看到的forker程序是一样的
so this is the exact same forker that we looked at in the stack canary case
我们可以用同样的攻击
we can continue that same attack
不仅能泄露栈金丝雀
to leak not just the canary
还能泄露
but also the
栈上指向存储数据的有效地址
various addresses on the stack that will point us to valid locations in memory where things are stored
好的，那么
all right so
让我们更深入地了解页偏移量覆盖
let's take a more in depth look at overwriting page offsets
这背后的关键原理
the key intuition behind this
是页面总是对齐的
is that pages are always aligned
它们总是和0x1000对齐
they're always aligned to 0x1000
他们是随机的
they're randomized
位置是随机的
but the location is randomized
但是该页的第一个字节的偏移量总是000
but the 1st byte of that page is always at 000 offset
页面的最后一个字节是F F F
and the last byte of the page is F F F
然后是其他的
and then everything else
那一页的实际位置
um the actual location of that page
是随机的，但与0x1000对齐
is randomized but aligned to ox 1000
可能的页面地址是
okay so possible page addresses are
这些是各种各样的怪物
are these various monstrosities
这可能是一个库地址
this is a possible address of a library
这可能是一个主二进制文件的地址
this is a possible address of a main binary
这可能是一些特殊的内核映射帮助器地址
this is a possible address of  some special kernel mapped helper region
我们会在以后的课上讲到
that we'll talk about in a future module
这可能是一个非位置无关的库地址
this is a possible location of a not position independent library binary
但结果是这三个零永远不会改变
but the upshot is these three zeros never change
如果有一段代码在二进制文件中的偏移量是0x137
if there is a piece of code that is 0x137 of an offset inside a binary
并且主二进制文件加载在这里
and the main binary is mount here
那个地址就是这些乱七八糟的137
that address will be all of this gunk 137
有趣的是你可以覆盖最后一个或者两个字节
and the interesting thing is that you can overwrite the last byte or the last 2 bytes
如果你只覆盖最后一个字节
if you overwrite the last byte
你可以重定向到指定位置
you can overwrite it with certainty
如果您想从二进制文件中的137重定向执行到145
if you want to redirect execution from 137 in the binary to 145
你可以很容易地把最后一个字节37覆盖成45
you can very easily just overwrite that last byte from 37 to 4 5
因为在小端序中
because in little endian
最后一个字节将是你覆盖的第一个字节
that last byte will be the 1st byte that you overwrite
如果你需要跳到更远的位置
if you need to make a wider jump
那你就得需要一点暴力破解了
then you'll need to brute force
你需要运气
you need to get lucky
你需要运行大约16次
you need to run it about 16 times
直到这最后的半字节与所要覆盖它的内容一致
until this last nibble lines up to what you expect to what you overwrote it with
因为通常一次覆盖一个字节
all right because you overwrite generally a byte at a time
举个例子
let me show you this
所以我编译了这个buffer_overflow
so I compiled my buffer overflow
当然，我想跳转（到win）
and I want to of course redirect execution from win
从main返回地址
from the return address of main
当main返回时，我想跳转到win函数
when main returns I wanted to jump to win
提醒一下，这个buffer_overflow代码长这样
and as remind this buffer overflow looks like this
有一个main函数
there's a main function
紧接着是一个win函数
and right afterwards there's a win function
反汇编一下
let's disassemble it
这是main函数在1189
here is main  at 1189
win函数在11c2处，这两个地址只有一字节差异
and at 11c2 is win one byte differs between those two addresses
gdb一下
let's GDB it
GDB将
GDB will
我马上就会提到
as I'll mention in a second
会自动禁用ASLR如果它可以，如果你有权限
will automatically disable ASLR if it can if you have permissions to do so
这对于调试非常有用
this is very useful for debugging
我们来看看
so let's look at
在main下断点
let's break in main
运行，好，现在在main，我们有5555 5555 4000
run okay so here we are in main we have  5555 5555 4000
所以当GDB禁用ASLR后，内存基址就是这个
so GDB has a base of this when it disables randomization
然后加上1189，这是main所在的位置
and then plus 1189 which is where main lives
1189，所以现在在这里
1189 and so here we are
我刚想起一个问题
I just realized a problem that I should have
让我们看看main的返回地址
let's look at the return address of main
main的返回地址是某个库的地址
the return address of main goes to some library somewhere
这不是我们在这个简单例子中想看到的
that's not what we want in this simple example
在这个简单的例子中，它为什么会返回到库中
the simple example  why does it go into the library
因为__libc_start_main调用了main
because __libc_start_main calls main
如果你对此感到困惑，回头看看我的进程生命周期基础课程
if this is confusing to you go back and look at my process life cycle fundamental lectures
我们把它改成一个vuln函数
let's make this a vuln function
让main调用vuln
let's make main called vuln
好了
okay
很简单的小变化
this is nice and simple very small change
main函数调用vuln函数
the main function just calls the vuln function
我们可以编译
we can compile this
太棒了
awesome
运行，我们在vuln下断点
run it all right now we're breaking vuln
哦，objdump看一下
oh let's objdump
在哪里
where
我的vuln函数在哪
where's my vuln function
oops
我刚才修改了什么
what did I just modify
啊，我改错了
ah I modified the wrong
我刚刚修改的forker.c
I modified an example for the wrong video
很抱歉
sorry about that
这是buffer_overflow.c
here's our buffer_overflow.c
然后编译
and here is the compilation
好酷
okay cool
现在我们有一个main函数调用一个会溢出的vuln函数
so now we have a main function that calls a vuln function that will have an overflow
我们像重定向到win函数
and we want to redirect our execution to win
我这么做（做这个修改）的原因是
the reason I did this is so that
vuln的返回地址将是一个地址
the return address of vuln will be an address
一个在main里的地址
the address an address in main
在main里的地址我们才能只改一个字节就跳到win函数
and that's where we can modify one byte to redirect to win
让我们来看看
so let's take a look
在vuln下断点
let's break in vuln
好了，运行
there we go we run
现在在vuln函数
we're in vuln
让我们看看栈上有什么
let's look at what is right on the stack
现在栈上的值是main函数中的地址 519b
right on stack is an address in main 519B
我打赌如果反汇编main
I bet if you disassemble main
它和之前一样从5189开始
it starts as 5189 as before
519b就在这个调用之后
and 519b is right after this call
这就是我们要返回到的位置
that's where we'll be returning to
如果反汇编win
if we disassemble win
win在51d7
win is at 51d7
如果你只覆盖这个最低有效字节
so if you overwrite just this least significant byte
也就是我现在要在GDB做的
which I'm about to do right now in GDB
我们可以这样做
we can do this
无符号char *
unsigned char star
rsp
RSP
=
equals
在哪来着？d7
ah where is it d7
现在看一下返回地址
okay now let's see what is our return address
boom如果继续运行
boom if you continue here
触发了win，打印了flag
we triggered the win call and printed the flag
当然，我们想要在漏洞利用的过程实现这个效果
so now of course we want to do this in the course of exploitation
我们要写一堆a，然后接着这个D7
we've got to write a bunch of A's and then this D7
让我们进入python
let's jump into python
导入pwn
import pwn
使用pwn.process启动buffer_overflow
pwn. process buffer_overflow
然后我们试着写
and then we will try to r.write
我们知道缓冲区是16字节
we know that the buffer is 16 bytes
可能是有一些填充
it's probably there's some padding
所以我们试试0x18 + \xd7
so let's try ox 18 plus x d seven
然后r.read
and then r.read
boom成了
boom victory
好了
all right
当然在GDB中我们知道这个地址
now of course in GDB we know this address
在GDB外，我们不知道这个地址
outside of GDB we didn't know that address
这就是神奇的地方
and that is the amazing thing
尽管不知道地址，我们还是可以
despite not knowing that address we were able to
只是稍微调整返回地址
just slightly tweaked that return value
如果原本的返回地址是这个555555555090，修改后的结果将是一个错误的地址
if I had tried to write this full 55555 it would be an incorrect address
实际的程序会被随机映射到某个地方
the actual program is mapped somewhere randomly
但只是通过调整最后一个字节
but just by tweaking by tweaking just the last byte
我就能重定向到合适的地方
I was able to redirect it properly
在更复杂的情况下
in more complex scenarios
你必须对最后两个字节进行微调，然后
you'll have to tweek the last two bytes and then
有一些不确定性
there's some uncertainty
你可能会破坏这个你不知道的值
you might end up corrupting this value which you don't know
运气好，覆盖前后的值这里正好相同
you have to get lucky and overwrited with what it was before
所以你要一直试
so you just keep trying
1/16的概率
one out of 16 times digitally speaking
你能成功
you should get it
好吧，假设你在做本地测试
alright let's say you're doing local testing
如何禁用ASLR
how do you disable ASLR
首先
well 1st of all
这样你就可以调试你的漏洞利用程序等等
so that you know of course you can debug your exploits and so forth
在不开启地址空间布局随机化的情况下调试
and not in the presence of address space layout randomization
然后相应地调整它们（漏洞利用程序）
and then adapt them accordingly
首先，如你所见，GDB默认是这样做的
1st of all as you saw GDB does it by default
如果程序设置了SUID，GDB将不能这样做
it will not be able to do it under any circumstances if the program is set UID
作业中有这样的情况
which the challenges for the homework problems are
因此，在使用GDB之前，您必须删除setuid位
so you will have to remove that setuid bit before using GDB
如果你想关闭ASLR
if you want ASLR to be turned off
你可以用chmod来做这个
you can do this with chmod
只要把它修改成普通的755
just chmod it to a normal you know 755
或者复制到其他地方
or copy it somewhere else
这将重置setuid位
that will reset the setuid bit
所以一定要小心
so just be careful
如果你不明白为什么GDB没有关闭ASLR，这就是原因
if you're confused why GDB isn't turning off ASLR that can be why
您也可以在pwntools中执行此操作
you can also do it in pwntools
启动程序时，ASLR = false即可
when you launch up a program just do ASLR equals false
它的原理与此非常相似
under the hood it does something very similar to this
你能用
you can which you can use
这个shell命令，你可以使用它来启动一个shell
there's a shell command which you can use to spin up a shell
这个shell禁用了ASLR
that doesn't have ASLR enabled
当然，这些对于setUID二进制文件都无关紧要
of course none of this matters for setUID binaries
它会忽略这些，并启用ASLR
it'll ignore whatever you're saying and happily enable ASLR
最大限度地提高setUID二进制文件的安全性
to maximize the security of setUID binaries
让我来展示一下最后一招
let me show you how this last one works
在普通的shell，我可以执行ldd /bin/true
so I am in my normal shell I can do ldd bin true
它（的地址）一直会随机化
and it keeps randomizing right
这个LDD是一个加载器调试器
this ldd is a loader debugger
它只是告诉你将在哪里加载库
it just tells you where libraries will be loaded
好了，它一直是随机的
alright so it keeps randomizing
如果我执行 setarch x86_64 -R /bin/bash。R代表随机化
if I do set arch x86_64 with R randomization bin bash
这（bash）也可以是任何其他程序
this can be any other process too
这个进程和它的所有子进程
this process now and all of its children
会被去随机化
are going to be derandomized
所以我可以这样做
so I can do this
我的电脑有点奇怪
something weird is going on in my computer
bin true
你可以看到它们都在同一个地方
and you can see it's all at the same place
使调试漏洞利用变得更加容易
makes it much easier for debugging exploits
当然，事后你可以让它们适配ASLR
and then of course you can adapt them to ASLR after the fact
这就是我们要讨论的ASLR
that's what we're going to talk about with ASLR
我希望
I hope that
你对现代的保护机制有了更好的理解
you got a bit of a better understanding of the modern mitigations
数据执行防护
data execution prevention
ASLR和栈金丝雀
ASLR and stack canaries
这三个功能
are really kind of the three features
经常用于保护可执行文件
that are used everywhere to protect executables
有一个新功能
there's a new feature coming in
我下一模块再讲
I will talk about it next module
叫控制流完整性
which is control flow integrity
这将是未来的一个重要角色
that is going to be a big player in the future
但我们稍后再谈
but we'll talk about that later